g.14
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center Archives
Joseph Marmash Papers
1931-1982
g.14
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center Archives
2.3 Linear feet 2 boxes
Joseph Marmash was an active member of the Baltimore, MD Ukrainian-American community over many decades. He was born to members of the first wave of Ukrainian immigrants to the US, and his involvement with the Ukrainian-American Citizens Club and other organizations and causes began in the 1930s. This collection documents some of these activities, as well as his extensive work helping to resettle Ukrainian Displaced Persons after World War II.
Marmash, Joseph, 1911-1999
Scope and Contents
This collection contains extensive documentation of the activities of the Ukrainian-American Citizens Club of Baltimore, MD and other Ukrainian-American organizations with which Joseph Marmash was involved. He also kept extremely detailed records of his work on behalf of the Maryland State Committee for the Resettlement of Displaced Persons. The latter contain a large amount of correspondence with numerous Ukrainian refugees either trying to resettle or that already resettled in Maryland, as well as with their employers. A significant fraction of the correspondence deals with complaints about poor living conditions, maltreatment and/or breach of contract by their employers.
Biographical/Historical note
Joseph Marmash was very active in the Ukrainian-American community of Baltimore, Maryland, and helped post-World War II refugees as a member of the Maryland State Committee for the Resettlement of Displaced Persons. He was born in 1911 in Maryland to a Ukrainian immigrant family. After completion of the 10th grade he began work for the Montgomery Ward mail order distribution center in Baltimore, eventually holding positions of supervisor and industrial engineer. He continued to work for Montgomery Ward through his retirement in 1976, with the exeption of a brief wartime position as a draftsman with the Bethlehem Steel Shipbuilding Company (1943-1945). His activities in the Ukrainian-American community included organizing the Ukrainian Youth Club in 1932, serving as president of the Ukrainian American Citizen's Club beginning in 1936, organizing and managing a Ukrainian-American softball team in 1937, and serving as president of Branch 320 of the Ukrainian National Association (1946-1952). In 1948 he was appointed by Maryland governor William Preston Lane as a representative to the Maryland State Committee for the Resettlement of Displaced Persons, and in 1949 he helped to organize and became the first president of the Baltimore branch of the Ukrainian Congress Committee of America.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in seven series, as follows:
Maryland State Committee for the Resettlement of Displaced Persons
Lemko Housing Corporation
American-Ukrainian Democratic Club of Maryland
All-Nations Day Festival
Ukrainian Education Association of Maryland
General papers and correspondence
Photographs
Related Archival Materials
The records of the United Ukrainian American Relief Committee for the immediate post-war time period can be found at the Immigration History Research Center (University of Minnesota, Twin Cities).
The records of the Ukrainian American Citizen's Club of Baltimore, Maryland (of which Joseph Marmash was a long-time president) can be found at the Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center Archives (collection g.23).
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for researcher use. Please contact the archivist (archives@ukrhec.org) for more information and to make arrangements.
Custodial History
Bequethed by Joseph Marmash to his daughter Diana Marmash Carico, who donated these materials to the Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center.
Ukrainian Congress Committee of America.; United Ukrainian American Relief Committee.; Ukrainian Americans--Maryland--Baltimore; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees
- Maryland State Committee for the Resettlement of Displaced Persons, 1948-1976, bulk 1949; Series 1.
  - Correspondence and records, 4 folders
    Scope and Contents
    Contains incoming and outgoing correspondence with numerous Ukrainian refugees either trying to resettle or that were already in Maryland, as well as with their employers. A significant fraction of the correspondence deals with complaints about poor living conditions, maltreatment and/or breach of contract by their employers. Many of these letters have been summarized or paraphrased by J. Marmash into English. It also includes correspondence with Governor Lane and Governor Theodore McKeldin, D. L. B. Fringer (Director of Employment Services Division, MD Department of Employment Security), Committee chair William F. Laukaitis, Dr. Walter Gallan (Executive Director, United Ukrainian American Relief Committee), and others. Also contains copies of MD State Committee meeting minutes, records of the Ukrainian Relief Committee of Baltimore, J. Marmash's notes from investigative visits with resettled DPs and their employers, correspondence related to the "I Am an American" Day Parade (May 15, 1949), and DP arrival lists (containing names, ages, occupations, and destinations).
    - 1948-March 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - April-May 1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - June-December 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1950-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Index card file, Circa 1949; Approximately 500 index cards. (Box 2)
    Contains 3"x5" index cards, each having information about a single resettled DP family, including their names, ages, occupations, country of origin, sponsor's name, and date of arrival.
- Lemko Housing Corporation, 1978-1982; Series 2.; 4 folders
  Records and other materials related to the Lemko Housing project, a subsidized housing development intended for Slavic senior citizens. It was initially to be built in the Canton neighborhood of Baltimore, but due to controversy and heated local opposition the site was eventually changed to an address in the Fell's Point neighborhood. Joseph Marmash was heavily involved with the project until his resignation from the board in August, 1981.
  - Records, 1978 - circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Bylaws, Letter of Intent, and other miscellaneous records.
  - Correspondence, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Incoming and outgoing correspondence with Senators Paul Sarbanes and Charles Mathias, Representatives Clarence Long, Barbara Mikulski, and other members of the Maryland Congressional delegation, copies of Department of Housing and Urban Development filings, and a letter to the editor.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Clippings primarily from the News American and the Baltimore Sun that detail the controversies around the Lemko Housing project.
  - Ephemera, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Brochures and application information for other subsidized housing projects. Newsletters from the Harkins Group construction company.
- American-Ukrainian Democratic Club of Maryland, 1960-1962; Series 3.; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Incoming and outgoing correspondence, including letters to Democratic political candidates informing them of the Club's endorsement, letters of congratulation, thank-you letter from Edward Garmatz, correspondence with Stephen Jarema regarding a national Ukrainian-American Democratic organization, and congressional district maps.
- All-Nations Day Festival, Bulk, 1953-1954; 1949-1974; Series 4.; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Correspondence and ephemera related to the "All-Nations Day Festival" at Gwynn Oak Park. Also includes a photograph of the event in 1949, as well as one from an unknown event in 1974.
- Ukrainian Education Association of Maryland, 1973-1981; Series 5. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  The Ukrainian Education Association of MD was responsible for the publication of the book "The Ukrainians of Maryland" (1977). This series contains meeting minutes and photocopied publications of the Association on various topics, as well as material related to the sale of the book to school libraries.
- General papers and correspondence, Series 6.
  - Correspondence, Bulk, 1951-1952; 1950-1964; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Incoming and outgoing corresponcence regarding matters related to the Ukrainian-American community, as well as correspondence in his official capacities in the Ukrainian-American Citizen's Club, the Ukrainian National Home and the Ukrainian Congress Committee of America (UCCA). Includes invitations to dignitaries to Ukrainian-American events (and their responses), invitations to participate in events from government officials and other organizations, correspondence with Julian Revay (UCCA), Dmytro Halychyn (UCCA and Ukrainian National Association), and what appears to be an undated draft of a speech.
  - UCCA address list, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    List of addresses and phone numbers of individuals who were either members of the Ukrainian Congress Committee of America, or who were on that organization's mailing list.
  - Writings, 1978 and undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Biographical statement and photocopies of two essays: "The Ukrainian American Citizens Club & Ukrainian National Home" and "Ukrainian Schools in Maryland".
  - Newspaper clippings, 1973-1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Clippings of articles on Ukrainian-related topics in English from Ukrainian-American newspapers (The Weekly, The Way), as well as from general circulation papers like The Baltimore Sun.
  - Ephemera, 1951-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Posters, flyers, leaflets, concert program, song lyrics, and other miscellaneous material. Also includes the "Constitution of the Ukrainian Students Society of Baltimore, Maryland".
- Photographs, 1931-circa 1985, bulk 1931- 1953; Series 7. (Oversize 1, Box 1, Folder 17)